hey folks Brett here this video is a
response to a recent patreon poll that
asked me to discuss 4th frontier ideas
game theory and the echo chamber that
makes recognition of our predicament and
civilizations so difficult to discuss so
the real problem is that we are faced
with an old obstacle that we have good
tools for dealing with and we are faced
with a new obstacle that we have no
tools for dealing with and the overlap
between those is what's putting us in
danger the human species is built to
move between niches populations have
regularly moved between niches over
evolutionary historical time but the
jumps are not necessarily smooth in
other words looking backwards it may
seem that a population has discovered a
new technology or a new landmass and it
has moved from doing one thing to
another and it all looks very good but
the historical record suffers from
survivor bias in the sense that we don't
see necessarily those fractions the
population that failed to make the jump
so the bias in what we have available
does not alert us to the full danger of
one of these transitions in our case
we've also built a technological
architecture that is simultaneously
fragile and very highly energized in
other words it was possible not
desirable but possible for ancestral
populations to go through a serious
bottleneck and to come out the better
for it on the other side even if a large
fraction of the population was lost in
the process of one of these things the
population could rebound on the other
side to an even larger size and so to us
it would look like a success but in our
case what we've done is we've
constructed these technological
structures like for example nuclear
power plants that require
constant maintenance and an input of
power in order to keep them from
exploding we can't have a collapse in
the midst of a series of nuclear
reactors that can't endure a week with
no tending so we've built a system that
is not conducive to our deploying our
core skillset the one that allows us to
chain from doing one thing to another so
the question of the fourth frontier is
several questions interrelated
one is is there somewhere to go is there
some new way that humanity could
organize itself that would be viable
that would satisfy the human population
both in terms of its physical needs but
also that would work for it people
emotionally so that they would feel good
in the context enough that they wouldn't
revolt against it
is there somewhere to go and then is
there a path that would actually allow
the transition assuming that there is
somewhere to go I believe the answer to
is there somewhere to go is clearly yes
that we can see from here
enough of the structure to prototype it
and that there is no obvious reason that
a prototype could not be revived refined
into a sustainable ongoing system for
Humanity a functional one that would
actually I believe feel excellent to the
participants I'm much less convinced
about the question of the path there
because although I think there are
conceivable paths there we are not built
to embark until signals that we have to
and those signals will come too late in
other words we are comfortable in modern
times because our basic needs are so
thoroughly taken care of the things that
would motivate an ancestral population
to rethink what it's doing hunger or
exposure to
climatic fluctuations that were
intolerable or something like that those
things don't happen to us we live in
buildings that keep us comfortable
throughout the year we are barely aware
that it's harvest season so we don't
know even if a harvest were to fail in
the wealthy part of the world food would
come from somewhere else and the only
detectable indication that we weren't
actually achieving sustainability at the
level of the calorie input would be a
spike in the price of food but we
wouldn't have the normal triggers that
would cause us to retool which would
almost inevitably involve a certain
amount of hunger so in the absence of
those signals we are liable to wait
imagining that we are better off
sticking with our current plan than
imagining taking the risk of up ending
that plan until the point that those
signals do arrive and my concern is that
the point at which signals as serious as
hunger arrive in the first world is a
point at which things have gone very
seriously awry and the technologies that
happen without our awareness the nuclear
reactors and other technologies that
actually our survival is contingent on
at this point those things will be in
danger of sudden spectacular failure at
the point that we as individual humans
begin to detect that things have gone
off the rails and that sets us up for
disaster so one of the things that I've
been interested in talking to different
audiences about is how to recognize that
although civilization functions very
well at a day to day level for many
people and the closer you are to being
powerful enough to motivate change the
more likely it is that civilization is
working for you
so alerting people to ways that even if
the somatic sense that things are
functional is very convincing that one
can detect that it
and go on very long in this manner that
our trajectory is not stable and that
the end result of continuing in this
direction will be catastrophe and that
it doesn't have to be that by
recognizing where we are heading we can
shift modes we can employ the toolkit
that our ancestors would have employed
to shift from one niche to another we
can employ that deliberately consciously
and intelligently and the earlier we do
it the less painful it will be in fact
one of the great tragedies that I think
we face is that because we have
somatically taken care of our basic
needs so effectively that we are maybe
thirty years too late in recognizing the
signs that we must change in order to
survive and that means the opportunities
to change are much more limited than
they would have been if we'd started 30
years ago and the risk of not making the
jump is that much greater nonetheless
it's not an argument against doing it
because we may be thirty years too late
but being forty years too late would be
vastly worse those who do not see that
necessity have an advantage over those
of us who do see it in the day-to-day
participation in the marketplace if you
imagine that there is no problem that
requires humanity's urgent attention
then you have all kinds of options if
you recognize that somehow whatever you
do day to day has to fit with some plan
for changing what humans do day to day
in the future
your options are much more limited and
so that advantage is particularly
hazardous in a market-based democracy
where power accrues to those who have
accumulated wealth if those who do not
see the necessity to change accumulate
wealth at a higher rate because
they are freer in their business lives
then their message that we do not need
to change begins to take hold as if it
were enlightened this is actually the
core of what conservatism is and I'm not
saying that there is never a moment for
conservatism there are moments in
history where conservatism is exactly
the right thing any moment at which your
system is so functional that you would
be making an error to change it because
your chances of making it worse vastly
exceed your chances of making it better
is a moment for conservatism but at the
moment what we have is a functional
system that cannot persist and therefore
must be changed but people who have a
conservative reaction to it we dare not
change those people have an economic
advantage and they therefore have a much
greater influence in the public dialogue
about where we are in history so one
thing that we must do is wake
conservatives to the hazard of the
trajectory we are on in spite of the
fact that the day to day signals seem
very positive about where we are for
many people at the same time we are
talking about the traditional blind spot
of conservatives where they sometimes
correctly and sometimes inaccurately see
the system as so functional that it
shouldn't be tinkered with we can also
point the lens at progressives at the
moment and recognize that although
progressives may in general be right
that it is a moment at which change is
necessary there does not seem to be a
coherence on the left about what sort of
change is desirable and one one talks to
liberals one frequently finds in modern
times that what they have is really just
a rehashing of traditional liberal
positions some of which have been
thoroughly discredited by history
so conservatives need to be awakened to
the necessity for us to change a system
that seems functional
and liberals need to be awakened to the
fact that the ideas that they always
imagined would make the world a good
stable functional place are inadequate
to the challenge and so both these sets
of people need to come together around
the idea that change is necessary but
nobody yet knows what that change should
look like hey folks if you like this
video click like subscribe to the
channel and if you feel like supporting
the creation of more content like this
head on over to my patreon page and sign
up at whatever level feels comfortable